[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to stowe everyone i am peter
limberg the steward of the stoa
still is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this very moment
and i promise jason i'm not going to get
all bored of uh or tired of saying that
um and today we're very lucky because we
got the wizard
himself uh at the stoa my buddy
jason fox uh for those of you who do not
know
jason fox he's a meta modern wizard
masquerading as a leadership
advisor uh he's a speaker facilitator
and author of the best-selling book how
to lead a quest
um he writes this amazing newsletter on
sub stack which i'll share
right here uh in the chats and
how today's going to go is um i'm going
to hand it over to jason a moment and
he's going to
share his thoughts on the theme of today
which is how to be a meta modern thought
leader
[Music]
and if you have any questions any time
when jason's talking just put in the
chat i will
call you to unmute yourself you can ask
your question directly to jason
if you do not want to be on youtube
because this will eventually be on
youtube
just indicate that when you write your
question in the chat and there's there's
going to be quite a few people
here today so just put like question or
cue before your question so i can kind
of filter them out
and feel free to plus one them um
yeah that being said i will allow jason
to unmute himself
and i will take you in how you doing my
friend
hey i'm good mate how are you thank you
for the song
it reminded me of the early pandemic
were times when there was this
existential dance party going on and
it's like my achilles heel like i get so
clammed up nervous when
when like dancing things happen i just
end up sitting there super straight so
but i love the magic themes it's very
good um
uh yeah maybe i'll just riff for a
little while um
like i'm hoping hoping that it might
evoke some questions amongst um
those gathered here at the very least um
pete you and i can riff for a little bit
um i'm hoping uh that
i signaled enough irony with the title
of this session
how to be a mental modern thought leader
what the [ __ ] you know
there's there's enough of us i imagine
that are savvy enough here to see the
[ __ ] that is laced throughout the
whole industry
the kind of pomposity and sincerity
that's espoused by folks that believe
they have the singular
you know nugget of truth before i get
into all that though um
i i i probably should define some terms
as is often the case as
us philosophers want life to do um when
i say
thought leader now in in the early days
it used to be kind of synonymous with
public intellectual and there was some
there was a nobility to the role and i
i found myself enamored by the notion of
folks out there
researching synthesizing distilling
packaging
and and kind of delivering um quality
distillations of
sense via the different modalities as a
speaker
a mentor an author a facilitator a coach
and
matt church a friend of mine and the
founder of thought leaders business
school
has been a big mentor for me in this in
this regard
but then as is the case for a lot of
things in this late capitalist society
social media
and the spectacle and all the other
forces started to warp what was
uh you know originally quite a noble
thing
and so now thought leadership in and of
itself
uh well we save what's happening with
ted talks when
any good thing once it once it lasts for
some time and gown has enough
attention runs the risk of becoming a
parody of itself
and that's kind of how i relate to the
notion of thought leadership now
thought leadership um and i say this i i
most of my revenue comes through making
appearances that um
i kind of visit enterprise land and show
up as a speaker a facilitator a coach
and my intent
here is i'd love to share what savvy
i've accrued so that you guys can get
better at
showing up in this arena i believe that
this arena even though
it is inundated with pseudoscience and
[ __ ]
and this kind of salience for things
that don't actually matter even though
that seems to be the norm
there's still a role that we can play
and there's a thing going on here kind
of like yancy strickler's
dark forest theory of the internet where
i feel as though
if we were to take um i'm presuming here
that there's a baseline familiarity with
metamodernism but i'll just do a quick
run through
um hansi frank's book the listening
society hits me at a time that
my my dad was passing away with cancer
and i was going through my own
existential crisis and this kind of
alchemy of things just
uh changed my you know kind of like what
david chapman might call it
an ontological remodeling wasn't fun but
um it changed the way i see things
if we think about modernity as a set of
values
and there's there's a lot of sincerity
there's a belief in rationality and
science and meritocracy and in the
individual
and this seems to be the dominant modus
for the thought leadership
industry and this is where we get the
motivational speakers the leadership
speakers the consultants the hero
consultants that appear
as though they have the single point of
truth and you know here's the
the neat linear five-step plan on how
you need to do things and
and then sometimes the post-modern
thought leader
public intellectual comes in and points
out accurately with apt critique
um the flaws in that kind of thinking
and brings a lot of skepticism to the
grand narratives that we espouse
the trouble is though whilst this
critique is apt
and needed and necessary it often
doesn't
lead to anything constructive it's just
ever more deconstruction
and then the meta modern thought leader
potentially appears
to do some sort of synthesis and
reconstruction i say that but i don't
necessarily believe it
this is also nascent and emergent and
for me my own path through this i kind
of i did a phd in motivation science i
then became a motivational speaker and
very all sincere and then i
started to become very jaded and very
pomo and then throughout all this i
realized ah actually
if we become deft in the ability to
cultivate a mythos
and a mythos is like a set of stories
that are told about ourselves that then
allow us to cloak ourselves trojan horse
style to smuggle in good
philosophical sensibilities into the
heart of enterprise land there's some
good change that we can make
and so that's kind of how i've learned
to play things
now as this uh thought little thing and
i think that there's a potential for a
lot of folks here too
rather than simply and i'll come back to
yancey strickler's dark forest theory of
the internet rather than
simply abandon all the mainstream um
open web sources which then leaves a
whole heap of people still
um subject to the predatory mechanisms
of uh
late capitalism we deny that arena our
influence
and as much as as much as it fills me
with a kind of
mild loathing i i do like to
to think that we can kind of you know
here we are in the cozy webs and we're
in the stower
and we we're able to cultivate uh
philosophical sensibilities druidic
sensibilities a kind of savviness
a deafness stoic principles and then yet
still we need to be able to navigate our
way back into the heart of enterprise
land so that we might be able to plant
some seeds and cause some mischief there
and um i guess i guess uh i've kind of
wrapped myself around
in in circles here in my own uh
definition around
all of this and i'm i'm hoping that i'm
causing enough provocations here to uh
get folks oh [ __ ] my um light has just
fallen out again
hopefully i'm um causing enough
provocations here for some questions to
emerge
um the risks in this industry are that
we can fall in love with our own myth
and we can we can lose the ironic
detachment the kind of the
ironic sincerity that allows us stuff to
work and if we cling too tightly to a
single point of truth and then we
start to espouse that and we start to
gain followers and all those things then
then a lot of the themes that uh peter
has written about in these letters
that just comes to life there's this
kind of booth and juxtaposition a dance
that we must do if we want to be
effective in this arena and sometimes
this translates to
intentionally sabotaging our efforts
sometimes it translates to
resisting the um the
the call to optimization there are
plenty of focus i know i can imagine
what's happening with peter
happens in my world but there's plenty
of folks that earnestly
suggest that there's ways that we can do
things to optimize you know with your
newsletter lists you can create all
sorts of fancy schemes and campaigns to
kind of drive real rep more revenue
but if we kind of come back to okay what
is the role of
a meta-modern thought leader and i'm
even
i'm hesitant to label it as such because
it's all quite emergent and uh and
nebulous and stuff
i would suggest that one of the roles
that we can do is to
bring complexity thinking into mix to
act as complexity practitioners and
philosopher poets
to awaken people to the notion that
there are multiple ways of seeing and
perhaps potentially
the result of our role is that we can
arrive at a richer synthesis
together or at least a protosynthesis
that is continually updated and renewed
i'm um this is one of the things before
we got into this peter i was like oh
cool i'm just going to riff
and talk and stuff and then i have this
classic zoom thing that
unless i'm kind of sharing content
i kind of yearn for this agent arena
kind of dance and so
in a moment i'm going to be turning and
asking you to consider some questions
and starting to get them in the
q and a thread i'll give you some
priming for the questions
um my intent this is this is an industry
and a modus
uh that is fraught with peril
psychological existential peril and yet
there is the potential for us to have
some good effect
um some of for example one of the i did
a
did some work for ceo of a financial
advisory group
and accounting firm wonderful wonderful
person i did that there it seemed like a
just a
typical job but then that led to deeper
conversations
that led to him reading the listening
society and sand talk
and uh he's now my accountant financial
advisor and
heavily interested in metamodernism and
exploring what
you know what role accountants and
financial advisors can play in helping
people transition from game a to game b
there's ripples that we can create by
introducing people to new ideas but
i guess sometimes the risk is that we
get so caught up in that complexity in
our philosophy that we
we don't we we're not approachable or as
accessible as we can be
and part of the challenge of being a
modern thought leader is this weird
hybridization of signaling
you've got to kind of appear on the
radar in the modernist landscape in
enterprise land
and you've got to have the language that
allows you to sneak past the cognitive
gatekeepers in an enterprise
and yet also at the same time you need
to be subtly signaling the irony that
says hey i know that you know that this
is kind of [ __ ] but at the same time
maybe we can smuggle in some good
sensibilities at the same time and this
is a funny dance that i
haphazardly seem to have done okay with
over time and maybe there's some
sensibilities to share that
and so in your questions i'm i'm really
i mean i'm open to any questions but i'm
hopeful for the 45 minutes that we'll
have remaining here
that there may be some of you thinking
hmm maybe i can
you know with this rich synthesis
uh this protosynthesis through the
various readings and experience and
expertise that you've accrued
maybe there's a way that you can channel
and show up in enterprise land or or
play the role as a thought leader with
irony and sincerity in a way that is
efficacious so as to
cultivate more of the sensibilities that
will bring us closer to our world more
curious and kind
i'm hoping that maybe there's some folks
there that could do with some
insight there i just certainly don't
have the answers i don't know how to be
a middleman thought leader i'm making
enough as i go
um half the time i disagree with myself
but
maybe in amongst the mess we you know
some insight can emerge
so with that super haphazard um
you know scattergun approach pete um
how did i go okay i think i was all over
the place there
i had this big imposter syndrome thing
going on because of all those superstars
you have on
in the store right that appear and they
like these galaxy mines as you call them
that just
espouse these beautiful constellations
of wisdom and stuff and you know
um i've mostly been impostering through
my whole life and
so here i am yet again i haven't i've
gotten away with it so far let's see how
the next 45 minutes goes
well you're in good company my friend
because i feel that every time i invite
a speaker and
as well um yeah like uh
so i have a few threads i want to take
you down but again if you have any
questions
i see some already in the chat just
throw them in the chat and then i'll
call you to meet yourself
so i think i told you that i have one
foot in the kind of the thought leader
you know
corporate land with being a dale
carnegie trainer i'm not active in it
um but when i was doing it and i was
kind of in this sandbox
it's like like i had to code switch you
know like yeah
um and so i guess i just i'll just a
general question how do you not lose
yourself in the code switching
and how do you maintain authenticity you
have any heuristics to know
when he said the irony when to kind of
just like speak like normie language
it's beautiful it's uh yeah it's exactly
the question this is the tension
and um one of the terms
one of the notions i got quite clear
this is like the most dangerous thing
i'm about to say here so take it with a
massive pinch yourself when i first
read this despite all the warnings uh it
was like crack for me
um for about a a month um
we need to be mindful of developmental
blindness and so what that means is
whenever we show up and work in an
audience
or work with a particular culture or a
group of people there's going to be a
mix of folks at different developmental
stages now i don't i don't actually
adhere to any particular model i think
that
every individual model is kind of it's
fraught to anchor to any of that but
just generally speaking
we're at apache levels of development
ourselves include and we all have much
more to learn
so often it's a kind of a calibration
like a
a situational orientation towards
relevance realization as
john vavaky might say there's this kind
of fluid depth
um probes signals that you kind of
respond to to get us get a read of where
folks are generally speaking though
my approach is kind of fox-like
in the sense that i don't actually have
strong opinions
um i have weak opinions that are
strongly held as venkatesh rao of ribbon
farm might describe it a hedgehog kind
that goes in
uh and there are a lot of hedgehog
thought leaders out there that
have a strong opinion and they have
products that are built around that and
they have things off the shelf and they
have a lot of
stuff um kind of anchored to a
particular program and then
and then they kind of come in and that's
that's the lens in which they see things
and i think that blinds them to
potentially what could emerge
so coming in with weak opinions being
able to shift dispositionally but the
things
in terms of a heuristic i'd be looking
for the the kind of the fractal truths
the kind of things that make sense at
different levels of complexity
um and that often translates to simple
heuristics like at the at the heart of
it
if we can get people to think and relate
with each other a little bit more
complexly
if we can encourage folks to be a little
bit more curious and kind
and if we can soften the
metric obsession and the linear rigidity
that seems to be so
um prevalent in in most modern
institutions and open people up to new
ways of thinking considering and seeing
then we're probably doing some good work
so at the heart of it that's that's kind
of that's the sensibility that i
keep returning to i don't know if that's
helpful at all um
but but it's something
and then one thing i noticed too doing
um the piggyback off that
when when i was doing kind of the the
training and kind of like the kind of
speaking stuff i noticed i didn't have
to do much you know
i relied on sort of the my talent stack
of being a good public speaker my acting
background
and i was saying like kind of kind of
like cliche stuff stuff that you know i
could stand behind
you know argue that i believe in uh but
they were cliche and then it was like oh
wow my god this is amazing stuff
and uh yeah and you know i i didn't have
um so there's a point of like
disappointment maybe even
boredom that i was experiencing in that
and i didn't have enough yeah the
opportunity to do the trojan horse
strategy yeah i wonder if you
wrestle with that yeah yeah so there's
this thing sometimes where you just you
just
your meta narrator is just sitting there
watching yourself thinking oh there you
go you
silly monkey going through that
pantomime performance again and
i mean there's like what i've learned as
a writer
um um from a meta modern lens because
we're kind of bringing multiple cells to
this because this kind of nebulous
cluster of different aspects of selfness
and so when i'm writing i enjoy
marginalia so i can have like a
mainstream thread and then the
marginality is where i can kind of bring
in
the year sands or yeah butts or the both
ends and just kind of
enrich and flourish it and i guess from
a speaking
modus uh which is a lot you know we
don't really quite have in zoom
there's different parts on the stage
there's all the gesticulation there's
there's extreme ways to communicate
irony even though you're saying
something quite cliche and sincere and
there's
and these little hat tips most of them
wash over the audience and the dry humor
doesn't really land but sometimes it
pings that little cluster of
of folks that stay around at the end and
then there's this kind of exchange of
ideas and senses and stuff and somehow
there's been this like
little little extra blossoming of
awakening and that's that's kind of the
things that you look for
but um but yeah it comes back to this um
i mean my frequent thing is that i tell
i'll rock
up and i'll share things and it's gone
over the head of too many people
um so yeah that's it that's
that's a tricky thing i don't really
quite know and you know that
i never want to dumb things down but
sometimes you need to kind of find the
more common fractal that people can
resonate and relate to
and um any themes
in the i guess the the corporate world
that is
alive right now like you know you mean
the thought leader or like just
leadership like
any ones that maybe have that
existential opening to use andrew
tager's word that you can kind of like
double click on and then yeah that's
nice um
okay so yeah there's always fads and
themes going through i mean you know
it was um disruption agile
transformation um
all the common things now there's a book
that really
changed my it accelerated my loathing
for the industry it's called
a book called winners take all i can't
remember who wrote it's the partner of
the author of um the uh the
art of gathering uh which is which is
also a very beautiful book but
this notion of winners take all you've
probably mentioned that peter is this
kind of like there is a theater of
innovation that so often happens in
enterprise land this kind of pan to mime
where
you know we say all the right things and
there's little hackathons and
experiments and stuff like that nothing
actually
changes um and that's something i'm i'm
kind of very hesitant to get swept up in
otherwise i just feel like some
propaganda puppet that's just dancing to
the tune it's harder to smuggle in the
sensibilities that way
i've been lucky enough to you know
there's something unfair
uh in terms of what you know and people
have an experience of you
i think you're doing this by the way
pete um uh sorry i'm i'm shorting you to
pete you're okay repeat or would you
refer peter
only only you can call me pete that's
that's the thing okay
okay okay um
uh that's better than stoic daddy i'm
not ready for that yet
um um there's something
there's something like it's it's i can't
even remember what i'm saying um anyway
there's um i literally can't remember
what i'm saying
um so uh on that note yes
you talk about the book winner takes all
that was um oh yeah yeah so that yeah
the the the realization that um
so when it comes to the themes it's like
every year there's a new
spin on the same old ships that's not
actually going to change anything and as
we all know we're in the midst of a meta
crisis things are getting increasingly
dire
and one of the challenging one of the
most challenging things is
like if if we dial up um
our furore at this there look we all
have different roles to play sometimes i
like people thinking about what mythic
role
we're playing in this current chapter of
our lives and society
and you know for example peter you're
doing a this beautiful role of this
gathering
people in this like meaning crisis as we
cohere and make sense together it's it's
beautiful and it's answering a very
very real felt need that has been
missing for some time
uh and if we think about some folks are
actually maybe their role is to draw
some attention to some things but as you
know with the memetic tribal wars and
the paper you've pioneered and
all of that sometimes an excess of
furore and
outrage doesn't actually help things and
sometimes i was writing down your latest
post you said
it's wise to be sneaky here so let's
sneak our way to communitus
and i i really like the role of
sneakiness of the surreptitious of the
kind of
i feel like there's a congruency to
complexity practitioner here where
instead of like coming up with a grand
plan and saying this is the way
we instead we we kind of we do the
tweaking we sense we kind of we
pull the levers sometimes this means we
smuggle our way in and we use some of
the language and the code that's
happening in enterprise land so that we
can start to subvert it
and the beautiful thing about most
complexity thinking when people really
start to contemplate that is that
was a dangerous thing and that your mind
can literally uh implode and you can
venture to the abyss and you know have
to cross the chasm of nihilism and all
of that but
but this complexity thing you just start
well i wrote a book called um how to
lead a quest which
uh the thesis was um that uh we need to
make distinctions between
meaningful progress and the delusion of
progress the delusion of progress
is where default thinking gets in the
way of meaningful progress and this is
where in many organizations it's much
more of a career advancement strategy to
broadcast you that you're doing the work
than it is to actually do the work
itself
and this creates a rich pandemic
business where everyone's busy but we're
not actually doing anything and
meaningful progress is that which brings
us closer to future relevance
and that as a kind of as a thought
bubble just
that's the seed to plant in there is
really
it's pernicious because what is
meaningful progress really what is
progress what is meaningful what do we
mean by this
in what context from whose perspective
and that question
for me i mean it's plagued me it
certainly hasn't made me more profitable
at all um
and none of this by the way is a pathway
to great profits this is more about
high level fulfillment in this role at
modest
modest business success this this
question of meaningful progress
i mean progress is kind of sneered out
from post-modernist from a you know the
modernist sense of progress from a
meta-modern sense it's
maybe there's something maybe it's
something we can move towards but then
again after seeing tyson young reporter
and reading his book
sand talk i'm a little bit more
skeptical about civilization nowadays
and so
as we dance in this transitionary phase
to the you know inevitable collapse of
modern society
it's it's tricky to figure out our role
but the more that we can
smuggle in philosophical sensibilities
and cultivate
you know savvy for complexity and the
more we can gather and cultivate
communities um
you know across different mimetic
tribals uh tribes
um that seems to be a good path for us
so i'm doing this thing you give me a
question i just kind of take it on this
like lovely walk through the park and
i don't know if i answer it but i create
enough distractions so yeah no one
notices
i'm following you on the on the side i
saw loving it um
uh yeah it reminds me of um steal the
culture
uh you know generally yeah yeah you to
be a trickster right
tricks to make this as well yeah right
um
so before i turn to the uh the questions
in the chat
um i wanted to ask you about kind of
psycho technologies
that inspired you and that maybe you use
um because you're you're the one person
that like i've been uh
admiring you from afar for a while just
the how you kind of pulled off
the the two worlds you know that kind of
the the trainer kind of like the
motivational speaker type role a thought
leader role and then the
kind of this meta-modern weirdo game b
sense making left type person and then
it seems like
you had maintained that integrity and
i'm like i i admire that
um and i'm curious if
for those of you who don't know there's
a lot of these kind of like authentic
relating practice we space practice like
circling empathy dialogue
empty circles restorative dialogues all
that type of stuff
um that kind of
give you that glimpse of communitas as i
put on the previous journal
um do you use any of the practices
yourself and do you apply them to
um what you do yeah that's a
yeah it's a beautiful question and the
the admiration is mutual by the way even
like back in the intellectual explorers
and times i was like
i was saying to my friend michael
bangerstein who's on this call here
who's based in toronto
it's like oh you guys have got to catch
up and it's like it's just it's cool to
see the world's kind of like
um merging um the yeah it's [ __ ] hard
it's really hard because um you know on
the one side you're surrounded by
earnest friends who just want you to
optimize what you do and just settle and
productize and just
you know accept that there are easier
ways to make money and that you can just
scale this
and do that and so on and then and then
on the other side you've got
um friends that uh you know are snorting
at the whole
uh complex uh you know the thought
leadership complex in the enterprise
land and stuff like that
and looking at you know the stuff that
you do with a bit of a bit of a lofty
sneer
um and uh and then in amongst it you've
got
the different arenas in which you i mean
i would
there was one time this is it seems so
ridiculous now but i got flown business
class
to bangkok to speak
at a conference um for a region where
they had all the regions leaders there
and the ceo end up speaking 40 minutes
overtime so
i spoke for 10 minutes and then i caught
my flame plane back
and this is all women in the space of 24
hours
big waste of money big weights of carbon
emissions
for the planet it's not something i
would do nowadays um
and and then as soon as i got back like
the first thing i remember doing is that
you know i had to clean the poos from
our cat and the cat litter
and there's this kind of you know big
transition between on stage and then
and the thing is you just gotta not fall
in like not
fall prey to narcissism not kind of like
the more i kind of relate to myself as
kind of this nebulous cluster of
multiple cells
and the better i seem to thrive in
flourish and
one of the things that's worked for me
in recent times
although i kind of i kind of screwed it
up a little bit as this is
retreating to the cozy web in some way
and just cultivating
a group of like-minded folks but i kind
of i did it
i did it in a way that ended up being
opening it up to everyone and then it
became like
quite a large number um and so i've just
recently kind of
canned that but there's finding an
affinity of a few folks that you can
trust and rely on i'm very lucky that
i've got a few of those folks in my life
and
a few of them are here that
that will cat you know folks like you
can have each other's backs and can
catch when you down and i think that
those i remember jim rupp was saying
something in this another one of his
game b rants about how we it's just
bizarre that we can get to adulthood and
many folks actually don't have many
close friends
and the thing you talk about communitas
and i think that
you know the um the cultivation of
friendships of uh what was it who was
that epictetus no
um who was the philosopher it's all
about um
aristotle no the good things in life
kind of uh
what was it um anyway we know what you
mean
there's something they're finding good
friendships cultivating like a sense of
like
these are the things that i kind of
rally to so i have my ups and downs
quite a bit but that seems to be the
safety net that works for me
all right um so let's pivot thanks for
the questions by the way i
really there's a sorry peter there's a
quality to those types of questions
like i've been yearning to talk about
that the the kind of the existential
challenges the psychological things of
how do you manage the cells and the
different arenas that
i just yeah i really appreciate those
questions and i find it really special
um so thank you
my pleasure uh and it's something that's
always on my mind given the
kind of like the code switching speaking
to all the memetic tribes and you know
um trying to relate to as much different
reality towns as possible
yeah and not not and not getting so i
mean there's a risk here that we can end
up reading and being exposed to such
brilliant ideas that we become
like harder to relate at the barbecue
you know the family bbq that's that's
going on there so this is
this being this is where i do think that
the trickster is a very good archetype
for us to keep in mind because the
trickster is a shape-shifter
in most mythologies and they're able to
kind of adapt to each different context
and i guess i guess embrace a multitude
of
of mythic roles so mm-hmm
sorry right so uh
let's go to the chats uh we got tim you
got a lot of plus ones tim if you can
unmute yourself and ask your question
yeah um hi jason long time no see
um look i i mean so there's a couple of
things that that hit for me
and i'll be fairly brief one is that
idea of sneakiness
and the whole trojan trojan horse thing
with big corporates i think is a really
interesting theme
to explore but the other thing that's
really coming to the front for me today
listening to this
is i mean
and it's implied in the topic but i
think thought leader is completely
obsolete
and and you know i think you know for if
we're operating in complex systems
we should be striving to be experiment
leaders and so
you know given you know i don't know if
we have a lot of ceos here today but
but we you know we may or may not but
what do you think about as
actions that we can be taking right now
today
that might help us move things forward
yeah thank you tim i love the question
and um and yeah that you're right i
thought the notion of thought leadership
and i would say even say that
unless we're talking about complicated
systems the notion of expertise is
a little bit um suspect as well
uh the thing that i look to
um it's a good question i mean
there's the distinction between a
complicated system has experts and
authorities and a single point of
whereas in a you know in this rich
complex adaptive systems that we find
ourselves in it's much more about being
explorers and experimenters
and tweakers and synthesizers um
i i i find that there's a complexity
practitioner by the name of sonia
blignort who
does work with dave snowden uh and the
kinetin thing and she has this beautiful
article on medium
and what i've learned as a complexity
practitioner
and i i personally i really like the
term complexity practitioner and i don't
think it's promulgated in the market
that well and i don't think folks
recognize it but
that's something that i often hold to as
the point of differentiation
as opposed to someone who's coming in
supposedly with all the answers the
complexity practitioner
doesn't have all the answers is aware
that the
it's a kind of a partnership process
it's something that requires some
sensing first there's
it's a practitioner too though because
there's one of the traps that all of us
can get
lost in is this the temptation to marvel
at complexity and that you know i can
find myself there whereas
in in an arena we actually need to you
know choosing to not choose is still a
choice that has implications in a
complex system and so
because we are part of it and it's
shaping us as we are shaping
it there's there's all sorts of
paradoxes and tensions we need to be
mindful of and
and thus you know the complexity
practitioner thing
and if anyone finds the article um
uh sonia blignort um complexity
practitioner
you can google that and put it in the
chat thread um this the sensibility
around that means that we're not
promising outcomes we're not sticky
we're not coming in with linear plans or
predetermined processes
we're coming in we're sensing and we're
trying to take notice of the patterns
that are emerging there and then we are
conducting those experiments
those weak probes and we are trying to
sense and assimilate some sort of sense
from it all
and this is interesting because it it
doesn't really play to the cards of the
thought leadership game of the expert
the charismatic hero that come in and
save the day
but i think that we're seeing a shift in
the code of what people look for
and one of my own sales strategies
you know when i'm in conversation with
folks that are considering
what may be a high value engagement
there's a lot
i'll often do some sort of cheeky
downward comparison
which will usually be some sort of
downward comparison where i'll point to
a large firm and say look you know
i'm sure you're considering different
options and there are folks out there
that have
well-established programs with a lot of
gravitas around them they can come in
they're very safe options because they
you know they can steamroll through
any anything there but you're probably
going to get a generic thing that's
going to cost you a lot of money and
there are folks out there that have
their own pet theories that think
they've got all the answers and can come
in there
and that may be fun for a little while
but i i sense that you know that
in six months time we're probably going
to be back in the same situation
and besides cultures or whatever thing
but you know it's complex we actually
need a much more sensitive approach so
that there's things there and i think
that if we collectively start to
i don't know terms are a tricky one
because if we adhere to them too tightly
they become corrupted and then you get
the game a [ __ ] come in and
scale it and then turn you know and then
we have to move to another term which is
why i call myself a wizard rather than a
thought leader
no one really like there's enough of a
sense of the archetype that people
understand oh wizard
okay um person who thinks a lot and
maybe you know
plays with magic and for me emergence is
a kind of magic so
it works in my remit but i don't know i
hope that
merry-go-round has given some insights
um thank you for the question i know
that you're
you know you are of mind and and one of
the great things that the store is doing
is actually
bringing a lot of more of this stuff to
the surface like the work of nora
bateson
the um tyson young reporter like there's
there's so much the savviness
that that's like this is the angle the
complexity angle is where we need to tap
into
but i'll say there's part of me that
kind of wants a lot of the modern
institutions to die
like there's there's there's some folks
that say
oh you know we need to fix our culture
here what will happen you know
and then like we can't afford to do this
and it's like well if you can't afford
to then good people
ought to leave or you know reconsider
their options and then before
but i guess you're going to have these
lifeless husks that keep on coasting by
unless some dramatic change happens so
i don't know i'm going way off track
here thanks for the question tim
thank you tim um
let's go with uh ben you just had a
question
uh jason thank you talk um
really resonates actually it's uh even
on a personal level sort of the uh
i have a gay a game a a game a life that
obviously runs
running marketing for large tech
companies basically selling enterprise
solutions so it's
it's steeped in that um and so all of
this the the trickster and
uh the um the multitudes and sort of
perspective
it definitely resonates um i had a
question about
your accountant uh scenario and i think
that this actually bears some interest
is there any deeper insight into
that sort of uh the accounting scenario
now i'll read on my question it was can
you speak more to the account
scenario as a model of bootstrapping
into the enterprise obviously just as
just
other words for trojan horsing into the
enterprise
um is there there there for that model
because i'm assuming this was passed on
this was diffused and this was kind of
scaled
deeper through that medium i would say
it was less
i love your question and and by the way
and i think the tension of game a game b
is something that we're all grappling
with it's just one of the extra
anxieties that we have in this
wonderful age that we live in um and and
the i would say it's less that was
passed through and diffused and more
that i
arrived and created the conditions for
such thoughts to be evoked
and so part of what a lot of the
thought leader role i'll go back to my
inverted commas since sam tim's
wonderful question because
when i say thought leader i don't
actually mean thought leader is just the
moniker that we can you know sneak our
way into the enterprise lane but
the role of the complexity practitioner
might be in
bringing the provocations and that that
for you like it might be exposing people
to ways of seeing and thinking that
weren't they weren't aware of before so
in my accountant
thing i did something for the whole
association within australia of
accountants
and it was this terrible thing that i
was supposed to speak before dinner but
they ended up serving dinner first and
so i was in this room full of drunk
people
not all were drunk uh and i was sharing
my stuff and it just resonated with that
two or three percent in the room like
deeply resonated so i got talking and
then from there
book exchanges you keep in touch i came
in and did an internal workshop
and then turned into a wonderful
friendship and this is the person that
actually introduced
me to sand talk way back before tyson
you know has gotten as popular as he is
now
uh and the types of experiments that are
happening internally within his business
are
experimenting with hierarchy or
hierarchical um setups of
of beginning to position to clients um
not just not just a you know game a plan
but maybe some game a b
things and all this stuff is it's kind
of it's a gentle it's a
it's a i can't point to any particular
case study but you can you can kind of
sense some of the ripples that we can we
can
play into which then comes back into
your role and
i i'd sometimes like to think that when
i'm speaking to an audience in
enterprise land that there are sleeper
agents in the room
and these are folks that have quietly
worked their way into positions of
influence so they can affect some really
great change and
but the trouble is and to quote um
patrick rothfuss the author of the name
of the wind um
basta one of the fey characters in there
says uh we understand how dangerous a
mask can be
we all become what we pretend to be and
one of the risks i see for us playing
this game which comes back to peter's
thing is that
if you wear the mask for too long you
can start to actually think and be an
act and essentially become that which
you seek to not become so like
this tension of managing it all
this this means that sometimes it pays
to
well i'm in my instance and pays to
deliberately self-sabotage me
uh my efforts sometimes so as to keep
things real and not get carried away and
i don't know what it might translate to
but you're in a good position to be able
to influence things and this is where i
see all the work that we can do
cultivating these sensibilities we can
diff yeah maybe diffuse is a nice thing
or kind of spread or like evoke or
you know help shape other worlds thanks
for the question
no great cool thank you uh
tim stewart uh you had a question
are you still here you can unmute
yourself
i was literally reposting someone else
let me find out who that was
well let me just read it you jason
referred to getting past the gatekeepers
in enterprise land but i
hazard to guess that your vantage is one
which
in which the individuals looking for
your services are relatively open to
change and enlightened perspectives
whereas why would they hire a coach
could you speak to specific experiences
where you had to try and crack
a relatively resistant crowd that
already knows better perhaps
but really don't have the commitment
sorry whoever asked that and i stole it
yeah it was john uh john would you like
to just add anything to that
um
you're mute yeah look
no worries tim um you've read the
question but i guess
you know the the uh conversations that's
happened in the meantime
um you know when we when we are on the
inside and i have been on the outside
working
not as a coach but you know external
consultants and now on the inside
and when you are perhaps one of those
two or three percent
that um desperately wish for change but
you're surrounded by people who already
know best they're
they've adopted the language of agile
and so they think they're already
operating
yeah we're pivoting yeah um and
so therefore it's just uh the
there's really no sense that they need
to change or if they do need to change
they already know how best to change and
so um you know it
in some sense we kind of i guess have to
resign ourselves to just playing the
position but then on the other hand you
know
desperately want to to be the agent of
that change as well and so i guess i was
asking whether you could
perhaps access some of the to the extent
that you've been in situations perhaps
where
the crowd is particularly reticent or oh
yeah
barely get invited in yeah totally yeah
yeah yeah yeah i'm
thank you good question and i i do tend
to work well with um
smart and skeptical audiences that have
seen it all before but if you put me
into
a room of sales people with alpha male
you know sales folks that looking for
their solution to close things and get
[ __ ] done and get their results in
it's it's a lot harder my strategy
is like there's always calibration like
you've always got a
like there's the agent arena you know
being being fit being um
able to orientate yourself to or work
with the reality that manifests if we
were to quote
um improv and keith abramson's work it's
like
you it's you got to work with what's in
front of you and so
a strategy is often for me if i come
back to this distinction between the
delusion of progress and that which
could be considered meaningful progress
that in the the context of constructive
discontent
where you recognize the discrepancy
discrepancy between where you currently
are and where you want to be
that there's this weird kind of
catalyzing that can happen
when you put certain things to language
it's hard to one see this kind of
translates to a burning platform or a
burning aspiration
and i mean you know you go
i mean this is the same effect with all
these things like david schmachenberger
um the
uh being more aware of the exponential
tech threat like the existential threat
of exponential technology
i can't unknow that now and there are
certain things that just
shape the way you do and i i just feel
like you know when you when you say that
you want to be the agent
i know you don't mean specifically but
there is a kind of a humility to this
um or even like a modern juxtaposition
of like a
inflated sense of self-importance with a
you know a bit of a glint
uh at your own you know ironic
self-importance there
is is that we actually got to be quite
humble sometimes it's
actually you know we come in and we
create some conditions and we evoke some
things and we make some tweaks
that people don't actually associate it
with us and that's fine you know
it's like there are different areas that
we can come to
and if we think about like a
particularly represent audience and i'm
going to come back to hansi frank's work
here
even though i've like come since come to
see some gaps uh
in the otherwise brilliant book which i
absolutely love and highly recommend to
everyone
um one of the things he talks about is
state um
what is the psychological state of folks
and if people are
reticent and you know the chances are
that maybe like
what can we do to enhance psychological
well-being what can we do to enhance a
sense of belongingness
because the more that people actually
feel well-rested and you know
well-nourished and in you know in a good
state the more likely they are to be
trusting and collaborative and creative
and so on and so
there's almost always something that can
be done it's just a calibration of
you know if i'm if i'm having a bunch of
you know pissed off
uh i don't know i don't know i'm trying
to think of some sort of
funny industry um uh cotton farmers that
uh you know blah um and i'm not gonna
come in with highfalutin complexity
theory
i'll probably like meet folks where
they're at dance and just try to like
suddenly
sneak things in i love the question um
yeah there's reticent audiences but yeah
it's just it's just a question of
adapting your motives
so that um you can bring about some sort
of shift
i hope that i hope that helps i mean
that's also like the trouble is you know
you've also you've got your client
you've got the person
the person who books you you've got the
audience itself then you've got yourself
as your own audience as well and
navigating that sometimes it's like
ticking enough the client boxes giving
what the you know giving what the
audience think they want
uh to feel good in the moment but also
kind of fulfilling your own needs and
that's the
that's one of the tensions to to juggle
here but it's something that i think
where you're we can all you know all of
us here
can do
all right uh rain you had a question
hey jason thanks thank you
maybe you can help me understand uh
within myself
why is it that i'm so much less
resistant to this idea of sneakiness
um than i am to other forms of of
strategy or manipulation
and the way i think is like there's a
lot of modernists that
um are um you know explicitly
uh talking about effectiveness and
implicatly
are manipulating and it seems to be
explicit manipulation but implicit um
effectiveness and goodwill so the
question sort of comes down to
what is the difference between
sneakiness and instrumentalism
in your view oh i love it i love it
um this is a great question i shall
ponder this further after this and
and try to write about this because um
gosh it irks me when i catch people
that that are sincerely using
uh kind of manipulative or hypnotherapy
or kind of like psychotechnology tools
that's like
they're sincerely using it as though
they don't know that the other parties
are doing it and that's just it just
irks me
if i was ever to deploy certain
techniques and methods um
i would probably draw attention to what
i'm doing like transparency
like uh like say for example that
downward comparison
example that i gave before where i'd
kind of list two of the other options
and in a kind of a downward comparison
way
i would often just point out the client
of course i'm saying this because i want
you to
work with me and i think we can do great
things together um
there's a way of it's kind of like
uh it's a way of exercising the demons
quickly and swiftly as they occur
so the the irony of sneakiness is if
you're being overt about your sneakiness
you get to be much more effective and
you get to kind of expunge yourself of
any of the ickiness of the process at
the same time
so i generally try to avoid anything
that makes me feel icky but as soon as i
find myself feeling icky
i'll draw attention to it and if this
was a
physical stage you can literally step to
the side and like look to
look to where you were and what you were
doing there's like like anyone who's
seen me on stage am i
quite fluid and in like in like
gesticule
form i am the i love this this kind of
like overtly pointing out like the
sneakiness
um i think the sneakiness is also open
uh like that the
implicit like the implications of
sneakiness
is if one is sneaking they're going
gently
they're being hyper aware of the
environment around them they're not
looking to draw attention to themselves
uh they're not looking to create a
ruckus and be loud and you know move
fast and break things it's it's a
different
dispositional approach to affecting
change
that is in in many ways it's
de-centering yourself which means you're
not you know
it's uh and that that stuff you know
that's probably why it appeals to you
and i imagine many folks here as opposed
to the
look at me and you can see a modernist
thought leader
just subscribe to their newsletters
they'll probably have about
uh a dozen photos of themselves in their
own newsletter they'll have quotes of
themselves saying their own quote to a
background photo of themselves making
the quote
um they'll talk about they'll probably
have an acronym built around their name
um to talk about their formula for
success or whatever it is
and that stuff is that stuff is like
it's hard to adhere to
mind you though there's a trap with a
postmodern mode
which can get so sneaky that you're
actually in the effective
altogether you're just scoffing and then
you are sitting in your corner with your
cigarette and you know
um sneering at the world um but not
actually necessarily showing up in the
places where you could be affecting
change
so there is a synthesis between the two
roles but the disposition of sneakiness
i don't know i think
i think it works well for us complexity
practitioners
thanks for the question i love it that's
a great question
um christian you had a question about
complexity
practitioners you're gonna mute yourself
yeah uh i had a question and someone
added to it so i'll
read her edition as well um
where's my question okay
is it possible to truly be a complexity
practitioner without the presence of
other complexity practitioners
and i say i'm trying to point at the
limitations of becoming
in isolation the underlying idea here
being that
how can you truly approach complexity
a singular place without you know
feedback and all those kinds of things
is there a trap in wanting to put on the
costume of being
a complexity practitioner and then
stephanie
adds to the question by asking
if this is true how can complexity
practitioners best
support co-coach one another in this
work
how can this interdependence be
accounted for in regards to our
livelihood
thanks for the update beautiful
questions lovely i love it
and uh i'm glad for this clarification
because yeah this this whole thing that
we've been talking about has been very
um almost individual you know it's
there's a there's a risk here that we
can fall into the trap thinking that oh
look you know
cast yourself like this and then you too
can be you know the call will go out and
then you'll
parachute in and work your magic and
then jet pack off into the sunset and
everyone's happier
it's not like that and i'm i'm hesitant
with
as again like a complexity practitioner
it's not necessarily something that
clicks it's a
an affinity a disposition uh we
only exist in uh relation to each other
to quote james cass
you know one cannot be human by oneself
and
our character has an inescapably fluid
thing we co-create each other here
and so you know think about this
complexity practitioner thing i wouldn't
be talking about it if i hadn't read the
post from
sonya blignon and i wouldn't have come
across her post if i hadn't listened to
um dave snowden a conversation with jim
wright and i
and there's this cascade of things and
we wouldn't be here because you know if
not for the work of
of peter and the store like all of this
stuff right we're co-creating each other
so that's inescapable like um
to quote david chapman if we think of
ourselves it's the
nebulous but patent so the boundaries to
self like is
isn't it there's an inherent
interconnectedness and yet there's also
pattern and distinction too
and so being aware that cool that's
that's the you know
organic realism kind of we're all in
this together
and and then it's about how can we be a
little bit more intentional around this
and so i think one of the things that
resonates for
many folks the stella and this is
something that i'm i'm you know
stumbling and trying to put my own
clarion calls out for too is
that um complexity practitioners or at
least
those who um have an affinity for that
disposition can kind of recognize each
other
and there's a lot of there's a lot of
things like i would look for subtly
um you know and when i find those folks
it's wonderful and we keep in touch
because
and but if i find like a belligerent
opinionated hedgehog then unlikely to
get
you know i'm not likely to give them a
call on the weekend and see how they're
going
the complexity practitioners generally
have uh
there's a softness or a gentleness in in
how we inquire things or
if we kind of if we're being a bit more
spirited it's done in an obviously
um like in a performative manner that's
transparent so
anyone who reads the start of handsy
frank's listening society we'll see that
the character of hansi frank starts with
this kind of
this extreme bombastity uh which is this
way of smuggling in beautiful sincerity
um i'm getting off track here
the complexity things yeah i think we
need to find each other because it's
bloody
it's freaking hard work like all the
forces are geared towards still this
life is complicated let's find the
absolute truth let's find
the fix you know let's let's proceed
with linear thinking
and the the ones of us that have a
little bit more savvy in this regard are
a lot rarer it seems
and we could do more to find each other
and i'd also add that um a lot of the
indigenous knowledges um have been
practicing
this stuff for uh many tens of thousands
of years so
um there's a lot of there's a lot of
savviness there that we could we could
actually learn from too
and i'm actually remiss in um
acknowledging and i just take this
moment to pay my respect to
um the custodians upon the land of which
we meet and
extend their solidarity to any first
nations folks gathered here today
any elders present past and emerging and
um
just acknowledge that yeah we're
fumbling around here and there's still
so much to learn
um thank you very much the question
awesome so we are approaching the hour
of about two minutes left
um is there any kind of closing thoughts
anything you would like to leave us with
um yeah thank you i think i
i started um
i'm really heartened by the the kind of
questions here and the
the sense this kind of uh nameless
quality of communitas that is being
cultivated here
i think i approach this in hindsight
with a little bit of um
i don't know in my own world it's very
easy to be the the kind of the
this is my smug you know just to take
this with a pinch of salt it's very easy
to kind of show up and be
like kind of clever and and you know
charismatic and smart and so on in
enterprise land
but amongst you guys i feel like the
imposter syndrome and i started this
like with extreme intimidation i know
you had bio on earlier today
i might look up to and then you have so
many galaxy mines here
but then swiftly it felt as though i
personally felt a deep
affinity for all of you here and i'd
just like to say thank you for gathering
and for
you know co-participating in this and
thank you peter for the wonderful work
that you're doing
um i'll make some close announcement
moment but yeah just to
comment on that like i i kind of view
these sort of sessions eventually going
to be like reverse sermons
you know someone comes in the galaxy
mind they they share their thoughts but
the quality of questions the quality of
minds that are congregating here
is is awesome uh and so it becomes this
sort of
like dialogue and you're just a vessel
to receive kind of like these these
questions um
so yeah thank you so much uh my friend
for coming uh
i've been trying to get jason the wizard
uh since the first started i think we
jumped on a zoom call like just that one
uh
a week after this so i'm very glad that
you you found your way here
um thank you so that being said just a
couple of
upcoming announcements for more events
you can go to the website the store.ca
sign up for the mailing list and if you
like to support us on patreon you can do
so
um a lot of awesome events coming up uh
so we have a sensemaker in residence
series
this is a four part series and we have a
lot of names that
mentioned today dave snowden he's the
sense maker for
september and he's coming in every
thursday at 2 p.m eastern time and all
those videos will be on youtube if you
can't make that
and we have um daniel gertz which is one
part of the hanzi fine art character
that
jason was mentioning uh and he's coming
in october monday at 10 p.m
uh eastern time to do meta modern deep
dives art spirituality sexuality and
faith so that's gonna be really cool
again those are four part series and
similar format as today
and on thursday we got joe norman coming
in at 8 p.m eastern time to talk about
applied complexity so
it's the theme this week for sure so you
can rsvp directly there and check out
the stone.ca
that being said jason stoyvillage
love you all thank you so much thanks
peter
thanks everyone